<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>

<!--
$Id: guide.xml 140 2008-10-31 21:49:50Z unsaved $

Copyright 2008 by the JWebMail Development Team and Sebastian Schaffert.

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE GUIDE SYSTEM "guide.dtd">

<GUIDE>
  <TITLE>JWebMail v1.0.1*</TITLE>
  <REVISION>$Revision: 140 $</REVISION>
  <AUTHOR>Blaine Simpson, blaine.simpson@admc.com</AUTHOR>
  <SECTION name="Contents" id="contents"><CONTENTS/></SECTION>
  <SECTION name="What is JWebMail" id="about">
    <P>
      JWebMail is a <A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_mail">web mail</A>
      server.
      Web mail allows an organization to provide a WWW interface for each user
      to his mailbox(es).
      Unlike Yahoo Mail, Hotmail, and Gmail, JWebMail presents a web interface
      to traditional email accounts which you or somebody else provide.
      The target email account servers may be restricted by
      JWebMail.
    </P> <P>
      By virtue of JWebMail being a pure Java appplication, it has excellent
      portability, scalability, and performance.
      We have designed JWebMail so that it works out-of-the-box for a home
      LAN setup by just dropping the .war file into your servlet container
      (which includes all modern application servers).
    </P>
    <SUBSECTION name="Use Cases" id="about:usecases">
      <P>Common use-cases
        <LIST>
          <ITEM>
            Serve JWebMail on the same host that your traditional email
            server runs on, to provide web access in addition to dedicated
            email client access.
          </ITEM>
          <ITEM>
            Run JWebMail to provide members Internet web access to their email
            accounts on an internal mail server.
          </ITEM>
          <ITEM>
            Run a single JWebMail server to allow for a single, unified
            interface to all of the email accounts for your users, whether
            the target email accounts are internal organizational accounts
            and/or external accounts.
          </ITEM>
        </LIST>
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>

    <SUBSECTION name="Features" id="about:features">
      <P>
        Features include:
        <LIST>
          <ITEM>Product is independent of the target email account
            <EM>provider(s)</EM>.</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Gives a user full access to his/her IMAP mailbox through a simple-to-use WWW interface</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Supports multiple folders on multiple hosts, depending on mail protocol used
            (IMAP supports different folders on the same host, POP doesn't)</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Supports SSL protocols <CODE>imaps</CODE> and <CODE>pop3s</CODE>.</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Sophisticated folder management system</ITEM>
          <ITEM>100% HTML 3.2/4.0 output, no Java on the Client side</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Supports multiple languages, configurable for each user</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Flexible template system to personalize look and feel and write new language files using XML and
            XSL</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Runs as a <EM>web application</EM> in a Java servlet container</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Improved session management keeps mail connections alive</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Performance, scalability, and portability
                of a pure Java application</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Usage of JavaMail-API ensures compatibility to many mail
                standards</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Open Source distribution allows easy customization</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Web-based administration interface</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Support for multiple virtual user domains</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Easily add new features through the JWebMail modular plugin concept
            (support for dependencies, hooking into URLs, etc)</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Application/Data separation allows for redeployments and
            upgrades without losing any configuration or user data.</ITEM>
        </LIST>
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>
  </SECTION>

  <SECTION name="Installation" id="install">
    <SUBSECTION name="Introduction" id="install:introduction">
      The basic installation instructions here can also be found in plain
      text format in the file INSTALL.txt in the distribution.
    </SUBSECTION>
    <SUBSECTION name="Requirements" id="install:requirements">
      <P>For running JWebMail you need the following software:
        <LIST>
          <ITEM>
            A mailserver for sending (SMTP) and receiving (IMAP) mails; by default,
            JWebMail will use <CODE>localhost</CODE> for both
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            A Java servlet container which supports the 2.4 servlet spec,
            and runs on a Java 1.5 or greater JVM (either JRE or JDK).
            Anything from a stripped down servlet-container
            like <A href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat</A>,
            to a J2EE application server like
            <A href="http://www.jboss.org/jbossas">JBoss</A> or
            <A href="http://www.ibm.com/software/webservers/appserv/was/">
              WebSphere</A> will work.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Your servlet container needs modern versions of the following libraries
            installed:
            <LIST>
              <ITEM>
                JavaMail API (typically <CODE>mailapi-*.jar</CODE>)
                You can download
                <A href="http://pub.admc.com/lib-repos/mailapi-1.4.1.jar">
                   version 1.4.1 of the JavaMail API library here</A>.
              </ITEM> <ITEM>
                JavaMail SMTP provider (typically <CODE>smtp-*.jar</CODE>).
                You can download
                <A href="http://pub.admc.com/lib-repos/smtp-1.4.1.jar">
                  version 1.4.1 of the SMTP library here</A>.
              </ITEM> <ITEM>
                JAF/Java Activation Framework
                (<EM>not necessary if your servlet container uses Java 1.6</EM>,
                since Java 1.6 includes the activation framework).
                Java 1.5-users can download
                <A href="http://pub.admc.com/lib-repos/jaf-1.1.1.jar">
                version 1.1.1 of JAF library here</A>.
              </ITEM>
            </LIST>
          </ITEM>
        </LIST>
      </P> <P>
        If you wish to build a custom app, or develop, you will also need a
        standalone Java JDK 1.5 or later, and Ant 1.7 or later, as described below.
        Any or no Java IDE will work.
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>
    <SUBSECTION name="Installing" id="install:intro">
      <P>
        There are separate sections below, depending on whether you want to
        just <EM>run</EM> JWebMail, or to build it on the command-line or
        with an IDE.
      </P>
    <SUBSUBSECTION name="Installing Application (binary install)"
                id="install:binary">
      <P>
        This is the preferred installation method if you just want to run
        JWebMail, and have no need to customize the application iteself.
      </P> <P>
        This installation is very simple:
      </P> <P>
        Install <CODE>jwebmail.war</CODE> as you would install any War file.
      </P> <P>
        With Tomcat, the easiest way is to use the Manager webapp, which serves
        http://localhost:8080/manager/html by default.  Log in and deploy the
        war using the Gui (you can see or add manager accounts in the file
        $CATALINA_BASE/config/tomcat-users.xml).
      </P> <P>
        For every application server that I know of, if you have auto-deploy on
        (usually the default mode) you can become the app-server <EM>owner</EM> (the
        account under which the server process(es) run), and just copy the war
        file into the webapp landing directory.  If you don't have access to that
        account, see your app server docs, because the war file permission
        requirements vary (if you have superuser privileges, you can always
        change the file to be owned by the app-server owner).  Rest assured,
        your app server has several easy ways to deploy war files.
      </P> <P>
        JWebMail is then available by visiting http://yourhost:PORT/jwebmail
        with a web browser.
      </P> <P>
        Please don't forget to visit the administration interface first. You can access
        it by browsing http://yourhost:PORT/jwebmail/admin.  Initial password
        is <CODE>Secret</CODE>.
      </P>
    </SUBSUBSECTION>
    <SUBSUBSECTION name="Build and Install from source" id="install:build">
      <P>
        JWebMail is compiled by using the Ant build-system.  You will need
        <A href="http://ant.apache.org/">Ant</A> version 1.7 or greater and
        <A href="http://java.sun.com/javase/">Java JDK 1.5 or greater</A>
        to build JWebMail.
      </P> <P>
        You can obtain the JWebMail source code by extracing a source code
        distribution package, or by exporting or checking out our code from
        SourceForge.  You can get our distro packages at 
        <A href="https://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2056">
        https://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2056</A>.
        You can use any Subversion client to get our trunk code from
        <CODE>https://jwebmail.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/jwebmail/trunk</CODE>.
      </P> <P>
        The following steps are required (for a quick-start):<NLIST>
          <ITEM>
            Set your JAVA_HOME environment variable (to the directory where the JDK is
            installed)
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Make sure that the <CODE>bin</CODE> directory of your Ant installation is in your
            search path.  Run "<CODE>ant -v</CODE>" to verify.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            You will need Internet access the first time you run the build, so that
            build process can download the needed third party libraries
            (automatically).
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Just run 'ant' to build a war file in subdirectory
            <CODE>dist</CODE>.
            If you don't have an
            <A href="http://ant.apache.org/ivy/">Ivy</A>
            jar file in your CLASSPATH, the Ant command
            above will display the simple command that you can copy-and-paste to your
            command line to satisfy it.
            <NOTE>
              An error message like
              <CODE>...doesn't support the nested "matches" element...</CODE>
              means you need to upgrade Ant to 1.7 or later.</NOTE>
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Deploy the file at <CODE>dist/jwebmail.jar</CODE> to your servlet container, as
            explained in the previous section.
            Alternatively, you set Ant property <CODE>exploded.dir</CODE>
            and deploy the exploded webapp to a live deployment directory.
            Since you are building software, we figure you
            are handy enough to figure this out without further instruction from us.
          </ITEM>
        </NLIST>
      </P> <P>
        Run "<CODE>ant -p</CODE>" for further possible targets that may be used.
        To customize any Ant properties, create a standard Java properties file in
        this directory with name <CODE>local.properties</CODE>.
        Most developers will want to use the targets
        <CODE>gen-guide</CODE> and <CODE>javadoc</CODE> to build documentation.
        (They get written to the <CODE>build/apidocs</CODE> and
        <CODE>doc</CODE> subdirectories respectively).
      </P> <P>
        Unless the version of the User's Guide you are reading is out-of-date,
        you probably won't need this, but...
        The <CODE>gen-guide</CODE> task requires the program "xsltproc".
        You have a few alternatives to access a User's Guide if you don't
        have <CODE>xsltproc</CODE>.
        <LIST>
          <ITEM>Read it online at <A href="http://jwebmail.sourceforge.net/jwebmail-guide.html">
              http://jwebmail.sourceforge.net/jwebmail-guide.html</A></ITEM>
          <ITEM>Use your own XSLT processor program to generate 
                jwebmail-guide.html file from
                the guide.* artifacts in the doc-src directory.</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Download the desired version of the binary distribution of
                JWebMail.  These include a pre-build User's Guide.</ITEM>
        </LIST>
      </P> <P>
        The build system uses
        <A href="http://ant.apache.org/ivy/">Apache Ivy</A>
        to fetch third party libraries.  The configuration allows you to
        change the library repository location by editing local.properties
        and ivy-settings.xml.  See
        <A href="http://ant.apache.org/ivy/">http://ant.apache.org/ivy/</A>
        for details about Apache Ivy.
      </P> <P>
        Code contributors must read and follow the coding conventions listed
        in the <CODE>conventions.txt</CODE> file located in the <CODE>doc</CODE>
        subdirectory.
        It's important to not submit files which should not be
        change-controlled, and to set the right Subversion file properties.
        The easiest way to accomplish this is to put
        the supplied file <CODE>samples/config-svn.txt</CODE> into
        place at <CODE>$HOME/.subversion/config</CODE> on UNIX-like OSes,
        or wherever your Subversion client wants it on Windows.
        When you submit code, always add a meaningful subversion commit
        message which very briefly describes what you have changed, added,
        or removed.
      </P>
    </SUBSUBSECTION>
    <SUBSUBSECTION name="IDE Setup" id="install:ide">
      <P>
        At this point in time, we only have the JWebMail pre-configured for
        Eclipse.
        Any developer who has a strong preference for a different IDE should
        be capable of getting things working in it.
        If you do this in a way to share the configuration in a fool-proof
        manner, like we do for Eclipse, please contact me to get these
        improvements into the code baseline.
      </P> <P>
        Here are the steps to start from 0 and get JWebMail building.
        Most developers will skip many of these steps because they probably
        already have some of the components in place.
        <NLIST>
          <ITEM>Install a 1.5 or later JDK and set a Windows env. variable for
            JAVA_HOME, with value of the absolute path to your JDK
            installation root.
            You can download a JDK from
            <A href="http://java.sun.com/javase/">Sun</A>.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Install or have deployment access to a 2.4-spec-compliant servlet
            container like
            <A href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat</A> version 6.
            (Could be installed on a different computer).
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Install a JDT variant of Eclipse, version 3.4.1 or later.
            I prefer the plain <EM>Java</EM> package, because it doesn't
            include tons of stuff that you will never use, like the much
            larger distributions have.
            After you extract the distribution, execute the startup binary
            once with the <CODE>-initialize</CODE> switch.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            To install Subversive, the Subversion client plugin,
            use pulldown menu <CODE>Help / Software Updates</CODE> and click
            the <CODE>Install</CODE> button.
            Bring up a web browser at the same time and browse to
            <A href="http://www.polarion.com/products/svn/subversive.php?src=eclipseproject">
    http://www.polarion.com/products/svn/subversive.php?src=eclipseproject</A>.
            Back in Eclipse, click the <CODE>Available Software</CODE> tab 
            and Add the two "required" URLs listed in the "Latest Release"
            section of that web page.
            Select the latest available release of each of the four following
            items and install them.<LIST>
              <ITEM>SVN Team Provider</ITEM>
              <ITEM>JDT Ignore Extensions</ITEM>
              <ITEM>Connectors / Subversive SVN Connectors</ITEM>
              <ITEM>Connectors / SVNKit</ITEM>
            </LIST>
            When done, you will be prompted to restart Eclipse.  Do so.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            After Eclipse restarts, use pulldown menu <CODE>File / Import</CODE>
            and import from Subversion.
            Enter URL of <CODE>https://jwebmail.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/jwebmail/trunk</CODE>
            and no other detals (unless you're a team developer).
            If it craps out, restart Eclipse and retry... or it could be a
            bad Internet connection to Sourceforge.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Get rid of any Eclipse views that you don't need.
            Use pulldown <CODE>Window / Show View / Ant</CODE>.
            Click the target icon in the Ant view toolbar to hide internal
            Ant targets.
            Right click in the view and add the Ant build file
            <CODE>build.xml</CODE> from the root directory of the project.
            At this point all of the listed Ant targets should work,
            except for <CODE>gen-guide</CODE> and <CODE>all</CODE>, if you
            don't have <CODE>xsltproc</CODE> installed.
            Double click on <CODE>jwebmail</CODE> to execute the default target,
            which builds the war file.
            You will probably also want to execute the target
            <CODE>javadoc</CODE> to build the JWebMail API spec docs with
            entry point of <CODE>build/apidocs/index.html</CODE>.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Now you just need to get IDE compilation working, and cooperating
            with the Ant build.
            Go to <CODE>Preferences / General / Workspace</CODE> to turn
            <CODE>Build automatically</CODE> off and <CODE>Refresh</CODE>
            and <CODE>Save</CODE> on.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Use pulldown <CODE>Project / Clean...</CODE> to clean just
            the <CODE>jwebmail</CODE> project...
            and turn off the nasty <CODE>Start a build immediately</CODE>
            button (definitely a bad thing for shared Ant setups).
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Execute the ant target <CODE>eclipse-setup</CODE> and set the
            build variable as you instructed in the console output.
          </ITEM> <ITEM>
            Anybody who will be contributing code to this project, or to any
            other project with professional standards should read the next
            section too.
          </ITEM>
        </NLIST>
      </P>
    </SUBSUBSECTION>
    </SUBSECTION>

    <SUBSECTION name="IDE Code Contributors" id="install:ide">
      <P>
        People contributing code to the JWebMail project must create code
        that isn't difficult for other developers to work with, and must
        commit resources in a way that doesn't clobber other workers.
        Even if you aren't going to commit code to our project,
        you're welcome to use these procedures if you just like developing
        like a professional, or if you are sharing with somebody else.
      </P> <P> <NLIST>
        <ITEM>
          Even though you are a graphical developer, you need to read
          and understand the development rules above in the
          <CODE>Build and Install from source</CODE> section bove.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Back to eclipse.
          A general tip is to be liberal with hitting <CODE>Apply</CODE>
          and <CODE>OK</CODE> when changing Eclipse preferences.
          It's much better now than with older versions, but Eclipse is known
          to sometimes <EM>not get</EM> your changes.
          If that happens, just repeat and make sure you apply.
          Back to the task at hand, go to
          <CODE>Windows / Preferences / Team / SVN / Properties Configuration</CODE>
          and Import the file <CODE>samples/config-svn.txt</CODE>.
          This file has specifically been massaged to do what it needs to do
          while accommodating several serious parsing bugs in the Eclipse
          Subversive plugin.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          The remaining items all involve importing Eclipse XML Java
          style profiles.
          <CODE>Window / Preferences / Java / Code Style</CODE>
          First, go to the <CODE>Clean Up</CODE> and Import the file
          <CODE>samples/cleanup-ecpro.xml</CODE>.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Go to the <CODE>Formatter</CODE> and Import the file
          <CODE>samples/formatter-ecpro.xml</CODE>.
          Note that this formatter disabled word-wrapping for Java files,
          because Eclipse does a truly terrible job at it.
          It doesn't even enforce the rules as it explains and exemplifies them.
          Sorry to say, but after running Eclipse's code formatter, you'll
          need to apply word-wrapping manually (according to
          <CODE>doc/conventions.txt</CODE>.
          (The formatter works perfectly well for Javadoc and non-Javadoc
          comments).
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Finally, go to <CODE>Code Templates</CODE>, but this time don't
          load the profile at the global level.
          That's because, whereas the other settings are good for any
          Java project, these templates may not be appropriate for other
          Java projects that you may work on in the same Eclipse workspace.
          The only known issues with the code templates is that they will
          insert useless blank Javadoc lines like "    *" if there are no
          tags for a method, and it will insert a blank line after {'s and
          before }'s.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Click on the <CODE>Configure Project Specific Settings...</CODE>.
          Select the <CODE>jwebmail</CODE> project and click <CODE>OK</CODE>.
          Click the <CODE>Enable project specific settings</CODE> checkbox.
          Import the file <CODE>samples/codetemplates-ecpro.xml</CODE>.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          In the upper tree, select <CODE>Comments / Types</CODE> and hit
          the <CODE>Edit...</CODE> button.
          (IMO it's rather counterintuitive that the lower box there is not
          an editable box-- you must hit the <CODE>Edit...</CODE> button to
          edit.
          Change the text "Your Name Here" to your name, spelled out and
          capitalized like that.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Before exiting the <CODE>Properties for jwebmail...</CODE> screen,
          make sure to check the <CODE>Automatically add comments...</CODE>
          button and click the <CODE>Apply</CODE> and <CODE>OK</CODE> buttons.
        </ITEM>
      </NLIST></P>
    </SUBSECTION>
    <SUBSECTION name="Logging setup" id="install:logging">
      <P>
        Webapp logging is best administered at the container level.
        Most servlet containers were designed to work this way, and many
        technology companies expend much effort to defeat Classloader
        design and manage logging with delivered application artifacts.
        Remember that logging settings are a runtime consideration which
        should be modifiable after deployment by operations personnel.
        JWebMail is exceptional in that it facilitates logging
      </P> <P>
        Webapp bundles just Apache Commons Logging.
        Commons Logging provides the front end for logging, where the
        JWebMail application sends log messages.
        Your servlet container will connect these generated messages to
        a logging <EM>back end</EM> to write log files, database records, or
        emails from them.
        If you have a straight-forward servlet container, and you have
        not added a logging product to it, then Commons Logging will
        also handle the back end in the container space, just logging
        to the console or stdout/stderr log with default settings.
        But it is very easy to improve on that.
        Some application servers have logging management utilities,
        and you can use them to pipe the JWebMail log entries to
        destinations using Gui tools or text files.
        You'll have to see your App Server documentation about these
        tools.
        Otherwise, you can put text files in container-level classloader
        directories to easily set up text, HTML, and even email-alert
        logging.
      </P> <P>
        I will explain how to set up really nice JWebMail logs using
        Log4J as the back end (container-side) logging product on
        Tomcat.  In my experience, everybody is satisfied with Log4j.
        The procedure is very much the same to use another logging
        back end product (see the Commons Logging documentation about
        how to do it).  The setup procedure is the same for other
        servlet containers (that don't force their logging management
        system on you), except you just need to find out where the
        system classpath directories are (or how to add them).
      </P> <P>Container logging setup with Log4j and Tomcat<LIST>
        <ITEM>
          The default container classpath directory on Tomcat 6.x
          is <CODE>CATALINA_HOME/lib</CODE> by default.
          I.e., the "lib" subdirectory
          of the Tomcat installation root directory.
          You can put both Jar files and in .class files (in package
          directory trees) into it.
          (You can add other classpath directories by changing the
          setting <CODE>common.loader</CODE> in the file
          <CODE>conf/catalina.properties</CODE>).
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Copy a recent version of the file
          <A HREF="http://pub.admc.com/lib-repos/log4j-1.2.15.jar">
          log4j.jar</A> into the servlet container classpath directory.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Copy a recent version of the file
          <A HREF="http://pub.admc.com/lib-repos/admc-log4j-1.2_2.jar">
          admc-log4j.jar</A> into the servlet container classpath directory.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Copy the file <CODE>log4j.xml</CODE> from the samples directory
          of your JWebMail distribution into the servlet container classpath directory.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Set the Java System Property <CODE>logdir.common</CODE> for Tomcat.
          Our <CODE>log4j.xml</CODE> file uses this variable to set the
          destination directory for log files independently of where Tomcat
          is started from.  The best way to set Java System Properties for
          Tomcat is by setting the environmental variable CATALINA_OPTS.
          Where to set this variable depends on how you start Tomcat.
          If you use one of Tomcat's startup scripts directly on the
          command-line, then set the variable according to these samples.
          On Windows,
          <P><CODE>
              CATALINA_OPTS="-Djava.awt.headless=true -Xms512m -Xmx1024m -XX:MaxPermSize=256m -Dlogdir.common=$HOME/logs"
          </CODE></P>
          On Unix,
          <P><CODE>
              set CATALINA_OPTS=-Djava.awt.headless=true -Xms512m -Xmx1024m -XX:MaxPermSize=256m -Dlogdir.common=c:/logs
          </CODE></P>
          The samples shows unrelated settings which are often useful.
          See the Tomcat docs for details about them.
        </ITEM> <ITEM>
          Restart Tomcat.
        </ITEM>
      </LIST>
        If you prefer working with .properties files instead of .xml files,
        you can make a <CODE>log4j.properties</CODE> file instead.
        See the Log4j documentation about how to set up email alerts
        with the SMTP appender, how to log to a database, etc.
      </P> <P>
        Be aware that the file (<CODE>log4j.xml</CODE> or
        <CODE>log4j.properties</CODE>) will control all messages which
        reach Log4j in the container space.
        If you have three other web apps deployed to this container without
        log4j jar files bundled, their log messages will also be filtered
        by this file.
      </P> <P>
        Regardless of the container and logging product, if you manage
        logging at the container level without a Gui, the server classpath
        file will be the central point of application log management for
        the container.
        You can use package names to route messages to application-specific
        destinations (files, emails, etc.).
        The only tricky part of container-managed logs is routing messages
        initiated by classes common to more than one webapp.
        This isn't the place to discuss how to route such messages, but
        you generally don't have to worry about it if your app catches all
        throwables, and you have the same app deployed more than
        once-at-a-time.
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>
  </SECTION>

  <SECTION name="Configuration" id="config">
    <P>
      JWebMail has an administration interface which allows you to perform
      several runtime administration tasks, including:
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>Changing all configuration settings</ITEM>
        <!--  At this time, it does not shut down the server "properly".
        <ITEM>Shutting down the server properly</ITEM>
        -->
        <ITEM>Adding, deleting or editing JWebMail virtual domains</ITEM>
        <ITEM>Adding, deleting or editing JWebMail users</ITEM>
        <ITEM>Getting status information</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      See the JWebMail Administrator Plugin section for details.
    </P>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="General information" id="install:servlet:general">
        <P>
          The JWebMail servlet is called <CODE>net.wastl.webmail.servlet.WebMailServlet</CODE>. This
          class is contained in the <CODE>webmail-servlet.jar</CODE> Java archive. Usually you will
          need all of the provided JAR files.
          JWebMail Servlet.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          JWebMail is being redesigned to entirely separate configuration data
          from the application.
          Be aware that if you change init parameters, or anything else in
          the application itself, those changes will be lost if you ever
          redeploy or upgrade the application.
        </NOTE>
        <P>
          The JWebMail servlet uses the following <CODE>initArgs</CODE>:
          <TABLE>
            <TR>
              <TD><CODE>webmail.plugin.path</CODE></TD>
              <TD>Path to the plugin directory</TD>
            </TR>
            <TR>
              <TD><CODE>webmail.auth.path</CODE></TD>
              <TD>Path to the authenticator directory </TD>
            </TR>
            <TR>
              <TD><CODE>webmail.data.path</CODE></TD> <TD>Path were data will be stored (this has to be
                writeable by the process owner of the webserver)</TD>
            </TR>
            <TR>
              <TD><CODE>webmail.lib.path</CODE></TD>
              <TD>Path to JWebMail libraries</TD>
            </TR>
            <TR>
              <TD><CODE>webmail.template.path</CODE></TD>
              <TD>Path to language dependent template files</TD>
            </TR>
            <TR>
              <TD><CODE>webmail.storage</CODE></TD>
              <TD>Set this to <CODE>net.wastl.webmail.storage.simple.SimpleStorage</CODE> for the simple
                storage. Other storage methods might come in the future</TD>
            </TR>
          </TABLE>
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>

    <SUBSECTION name="Storage Methods" id="install:mysql">
      <P>
        By default, when you install the web application, a XML storage
        are will be set up under the servlet container owner's home
        directory.
        The location, and many other things can be changed, but data should
        not be written under the context root (appication deployment directory).
      </P>
      <NOTE>
        A database storage option (JDBC) is planned, but implementation has not
        yet begun.
      </NOTE>
<!--      <P>
        There are also several ways to store data:
        <LIST>
          <ITEM>
            You could use the simple file-based storage which stores configuration data in XML documents
            and is very easy to set up, but perhaps not very fast.
          </ITEM>
          <ITEM>
            The performance method however is to store the configuration in a SQL database. Currently
            only MySQL is supported, but it is easy to implement storage on Oracle or PostgreSQL.
            Using a SQL database for storage has several advantages which I will describe below.
          </ITEM>
        </LIST>
      </P>-->
<!--      <P>
        A more performant method is JWebMail's MySQL storage where the data is stored in a MySQL database
        instead. This has all the advantages of a standardized database management system plus a smaller
        memory footprint (per session) since data doesn't need to be cached.
      </P>

      <SUBSUBSECTION name="Why and when use JWebMail with MySQL" id="install:mysql:advantages">
        <P>
          Using MySQL to store the JWebMail data has several advantages, e.g.:
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>User configuration is compatible over different JWebMail versions</ITEM>
            <ITEM>DBMS allow easy backup and management</ITEM>
            <ITEM>DBMS might be faster than file access</ITEM>
            <ITEM>You can change the JWebMail configuration with any tool you like (you can
              edit users even while JWebMail is running, changes are active immediately)</ITEM>
            <ITEM>you could write simple PHP3 or Perl scripts that perform some kind of user
              creation, perhaps asking the user for extra information like address etc and
              storing that separately</ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          Clearly, this also has some disadvantages:
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>You will have to do some extra configuration work to set up MySQL as well as
              JWebMail before you can start</ITEM>
            <ITEM>DBMS also might be slower than file access, depending on configuration</ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          When you should consider using MySQL:
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>You have a large userbase</ITEM>
            <ITEM>You are running MySQL commercially</ITEM>
            <ITEM>You already have a (My)SQL database that stores user data (e.g. addresses,
              passwords, ...) and want to give your users JWebMail access</ITEM>
            <ITEM>You use JWebMail on a load balancing Apache server as servlet. Thus you can set
              up an additional MySQL server that stores all the data.</ITEM>
            <ITEM>etc.</ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="Preparing MySQL" id="install:mysql:prepare">
        <P>
          This document assumes that you already have a running MySQL server. If you
          don't, please set up MySQL and consult the documents provided with it.
        </P>
        <P>
          <NLIST>
            <ITEM>
              Set up a user/password for webmail that has access from the host WebMail
              will be running on (don't forget to <CODE>FLUSH PRIVILEGES</CODE> after that).
              Give it all privileges (i.e. set everything to 'Y'=). You may change that
              to access only the "webmail"-database after the database is set up.
            </ITEM>
            <ITEM>
              In the JWebMail contrib directory, have a look at the file mysql_scheme.sql.
              This file contains the DDL statements for creating a database called
              "webmail" and creating the necessary tables and relations. You might want
              to change the database name to something different than "webmail"
            </ITEM>
            <ITEM>
              Execute <CODE>mysql -u [webmailuser] -p &lt; mysql_scheme.sql</CODE>.
              Please substitute [webmailuser] with the user you configured in step 1.<BR/>
              This will first ask you for the password that you gave the webmail user in
              step 1 and then execute the DDL statements.
            </ITEM>
          </NLIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          MySQL is now set up to work with JWebMail.
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="Setting up JWebMail for use with MySQL" id="install:mysql:webmail">
        <P>
          Setting up JWebMail is quite simple. All changes will be done in the startup
          script <CODE>webmail.sh</CODE> (or <CODE>webmail.bat</CODE> under Windows or initArgs
          in case of a servlet installation) in the bin/ directory. The corresponding servlet configuration
          options are given in "(" and ")".
        </P>
        <P>
          <NLIST>
            <ITEM>Change the value of the <CODE>STORAGE</CODE> variable
              (or <CODE>webmail.storage</CODE> initArg) to
              <CODE>net.wastl.webmail.storage.mysql.MySQLStorage</CODE>
            </ITEM>
            <ITEM>
              Change the variables <CODE>SQL_LOGIN</CODE> and <CODE>SQL_PASS</CODE>
              (or <CODE>webmail.storage.sqllogin</CODE> and <CODE> webmail.storage.sqlpass</CODE> initArgs)
              to the values you configured in section 4, step 1
            </ITEM>
            <ITEM>
              Change the <CODE>SQL_HOST</CODE> variable (or the <CODE>webmail.storage.sqlhost</CODE> initArg)
              to the DNS name of the MySQL server (most likely <CODE>localhost</CODE> is just fine if
              you only have a single server)
            </ITEM>
            <ITEM>
              Possibly change the value of <CODE>SQL_DB</CODE> (or <CODE>webmail.storage.sqldb</CODE>) to
              another database name (whatever you configured in section 4, step 2)
            </ITEM>
          </NLIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          Now you should be able to start WebMail standalone with "./webmail.sh".
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="Further suggestions" id="install:mysql:suggestions">
        <P>
          If you are also running Apache with PHP3 on the same (or a different) host:
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>
              Consider fetching "phpMyAdmin" (see freshmeat.net). It gives you a web-based
              interface for changing all kinds of MySQL data, including the WebMail
              configuration
            </ITEM>
            <ITEM>
              If you want to provide some logon scheme for new users to logon, you can
              write that by yourself using PHP3 without too much trouble.
            </ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          Also, you can write your own set of administration tools in Perl (or other
          languages).
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="WebMail SQL Scheme" id="install:mysql:sqlscheme">
        <P>
          The JWebMail SQL scheme is not yet well documented, but not too difficult to
          understand. It consists of the relations "users2userdata" and "users2mailhosts"
          that connect the data tables as well as the data tables "users", "userdata"
          and "mailhosts" containing the real data.
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>-->
    </SUBSECTION>

    <SUBSECTION name="JWebMail Administrator Plugin" id="config:admin">
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="Connecting" id="config:admin:connecting">
        <P>
          You can connect to the administration interface with your browser by simply entering
          the URL <CODE>http(s)://webmail_server:port/jwebmail/admin</CODE> in the address field of your browser.
          (set http/https and replace webmail_server and port with the correct values).
        </P>
        <P>
          You'll be presented the administrator's login screen then. Enter the password there
          (on first startup the password is "Secret") and click the login button. You should see
          the system settings form then.
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="System Settings" id="config:admin:system">
        <P>
          The first page gives you a list of JWebMail system variables and their values. You can
          change any variables you like (there is a short description for each of them) and then
          hit the submit button on the bottom of the page.
        </P>
        <P>
          There are basically 4 kinds of input fields (although you will probably only recognize
          2 on first look):
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>simple text input fields</ITEM>
            <ITEM>drop down selects</ITEM>
            <ITEM>integer input fields (look like text input fields)</ITEM>
            <ITEM>password input fields (look like text input fields and show the encrypted password!)</ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          All of these fields will check whether the value entered is (more or less) correct if you submit
          the form.
        </P>
        <P>
          <NOTE>Special note on password fields: The password is shown encrypted (Unix crypt()), but
            if you want to change your password, please enter it in plain text. It will then show
            up encrypted again, after you hit the submit button (but still be the password you just
            entered).</NOTE>
        </P>
        <!--  Need to look into it, but Shutdown is badly broken.
        It could well be that these functions were never intended to work in a
        servlet container.
        <P>
          To shutdown or restart the JWebMail server, enter the time in seconds until the action
          will be performed and hit the appropriate button ("SHUTDOWN" or "REBOOT").
          <STRONG>ATTENTION</STRONG>: You will not get anything like an answer after you do this
          (since you are shutting down the server this is quite difficult) and you will not be asked
          whether you really want to do this! Most likely you will get a "connection timed out" or
          "document contains no data" dialog.
        </P>
        -->
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="JWebMail Virtual Domain Support" id="config:admin:vdom">
        <P>
          Virtual Domains in JWebMail are a quite new concept (thanks to Oswaldo E. Aguirre M. for
          the idea).
        </P>
        <P>
          They basically provide the following features:
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>users are associated to a domain (even if you only have one domain)</ITEM>
            <ITEM>each domain can have its own authentication host (if IMAP/POP authentication is used)</ITEM>
            <ITEM>the administrator of JWebMail can impose certain restrictions on users of a JWebMail
              domain. e.g. you can restrict the hosts where users may connect to here</ITEM>
            <ITEM>each domain has its own default host where the user's primary folder will be found</ITEM>
            <ITEM>the user's default email address will be set to
              "<CODE>user@domain</CODE>"</ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          Naturally, with this concept you will need to have at least one domain even if you don't
          plan to use virtual domains really.
        </P>
        <P>
          The JWebMail virtual domain setup form is quite simple and self explanatory, I think.
          There is one column where you have to enter the domain name, one where you have to
          enter this domain's default host (user's primary folder host), one for the authenti-
          cation host (not necessarily the same as the default host), and some fields that
          control the restrictions for users of this domain. With the checkbox, you can turn on/off
          host restriction completely, in the allowed hosts column, you can enter a comma-separated
          list of domains/hosts where users may access IMAP folders (e.g. "wastl.net" would allow
          them to use "mail.wastl.net" and "pop.wastl.net" while setting it to "mail.wastl.net"
          would just allow "mail.wastl.net" (and certainly "imap.mail.watl.net") and so on (suffix
          is matched to say it simple)).
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="Editing Users" id="config:admin:users">
        <P>
          You can add, edit and delete users from the administration interface (Note that you don't
          have to create users before they may use JWebMail since they get default settings when they
          first log on authenticating against IMAP, POP or Unix).
        </P>
        <P>
          To create a user,
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>enter the user name and the domain in the user field (in the form "<CODE>user@domain</CODE>")</ITEM>
            <ITEM>optionally change all the other fields from the default settings</ITEM>
            <ITEM>hit the create/edit button on the bottom of the page</ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          To edit a user,
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>select the user in the drop down menu OR enter the user name (with domain) in the short
              text field</ITEM>
            <ITEM>edit the user settings</ITEM>
            <ITEM>hit the create/edit button on the bottom of the page</ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
        <P>
          To delete a user,
          <LIST>
            <ITEM>select the user in the drop down menu OR enter the user name (with domain) in the short
              text field</ITEM>
            <ITEM>Hit the delete button</ITEM>
          </LIST>
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
      <SUBSUBSECTION name="Viewing JWebMail Status" id="config:admin:status">
        <P>
          Last but not least you can get an overview of currently active sessions with
          the "view sessions" link. You will get some status information there as well as
          the possibility to explicitly kill an active session (whatever maybe the reason).
          Please be careful however with this feature, as you are very likely to kill a
          session that is currently in use and its user will probably not be very happy about
          that. The sessions will expire after a configured time anyway.
        </P>
        <P>
          The Administrator Interface is currently available in English only, but the
          templates are already prepared for translation The system's default language will then be
          used (determined by the LANG environment setting).
        </P>
        <P>
          I hope the rest is quite self explanatory at the moment, but I'll add some
          documentation later.
        </P>
      </SUBSUBSECTION>
    </SUBSECTION>

    <!-- This probably should not work in a Servlet Container:
    <SUBSECTION name="File-Based Shutdown" id="config:admin:shutdown">
      <P>
        You can initiate a JWebMail shutdown when you create a file "shutdown"
        (or whatever you configured) in the data directory with only the
        admin password in it. This option can be disabled. It is useful in
        automatic system startup/shutdown.
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>
    -->
  </SECTION>


  <SECTION name="User Authentication" id="auth">
    <P>
      JWebMail supports extended user authentication. At the moment, the
      following authentication methods are supported:
      <LIST>
        <ITEM><STRONG>SIMPLE</STRONG>: Use JWebMail's former authentication method. Password is only
          checked against the user's configuration. The user may change his password from within JWebMail</ITEM>
        <ITEM><STRONG>IMAP</STRONG>: Check login/password on a remote IMAP host. JWebMail tries to
          login on a remote IMAP host with the given login and password.<BR/>
          If login fails, JWebMail doesn't allow access.</ITEM>
        <ITEM><STRONG>POP</STRONG>: Same for a POP3 server</ITEM>
        <ITEM><STRONG>UNIX</STRONG>: Check login/password using Unix's login facility.
          login/password are checked against the Unix passwd/shadow files.<BR/>
          Note: JWebMail must be run as user root to use Unix Authentication</ITEM>
      </LIST>
    </P>
    <P>
      Changing authentication method can be achieved using the Administration
      Interface and changing the <CODE>AUTH</CODE> variable.
      For IMAP authentication there is an extra configuration variable called
      <CODE>AUTHHOST</CODE>.
    </P>
  </SECTION>


  <SECTION name="Usage" id="usage">
    <SUBSECTION name="General Usage" id="usage:general">
      <P>
        The JWebMail daemon listens on whatever port you have configure.
        Just point your browser´s URL to http://yourhost:yourport/jwebmail
        and see the login screen.
      </P>
      <P>
        A user will get the password he logs in with the first time. Passwords
        may be changed by the user in the options dialog.
        JWebMail will try to establish a default connection to the configured
        default IMAP host with the user ID and password it was given, so it may
        be useful to use the same ID and password as on the IMAP host.
      </P>
      <P>
        For further information, just click on the "?" at the navigation bar.
      </P>
      <P>
        JWebMail should also work with Proxy Servers and other Clients than
        Netscape Communicator.
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>

    <SUBSECTION name="Folders" id="usage:folders">
      <P>
        JWebMail supports as many IMAP folders on as many different hosts you like.
      </P>
      <P>
        JWebMail mailboxes are configured by each user, however the administrator can
        change the default mailbox for each virtual domain. The default mailbox is the
        mailbox the user gets on the first login. He can than choose to remove it at any time
        and also add other mailboxes (the administrator can restrict that in the virtual
        domain configuration).
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>
  </SECTION>


  <SECTION name="Different Languages, Translating JWebMail" id="lang">
    <P>
      JWebMail supports the usage of different languages on a per user basis.
      Since v0.6.0 JWebMail scans for available languages automatically and adds
      the corresponding locales to the user's setup dialog ("de" will add the
      locales "de_DE", "de_AT", "de_CH", ...).<BR/>
      To translate JWebMail to a new language, please read the file "Translating"
      in the developers' documentation (source only).
    </P>
  </SECTION>


  <SECTION name="Notes" id="notes">
    <SUBSECTION name="JWebMail Status" id="notes:status">
      <P>
        JWebMail Pre-1.0.1 is BETA.
      </P>
      <P>
        Some features on the wish-list are
        <LIST>
          <ITEM>Captcha</ITEM> to prevent robots, trojans, and miners from
            sapping our servers.
          <ITEM>JDBC Integration</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Refactor and modernize the authentication methods</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Different XSL stylesheets to convert the JWebMail UI to other
            formats than HTML (perhaps WML for mobile phones)</ITEM>
          <ITEM>PGP</ITEM>
          <ITEM><EM>Extras</EM> like calendar and so on
            (will be realized as JWebMail Plugins)</ITEM>
        </LIST>
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>
    <SUBSECTION name="Changes" id="notes:changes">
      <P>
        See the file <CODE>changes.txt</CODE> for a list of changes in the different
        JWebMail releases.
      </P>
    </SUBSECTION>
  </SECTION>

  <SECTION name="License" id="license">
        <P>
      JWebMail is copyright 2008 by the JWebMail Development Team and Sebastian Schaffert.
    </P>
        <P>
      The base JWebMail product
      is distributed under the terms of the Apache 2.0 license.
      You can find a copy in the file <A HREF="LICENSE.txt">LICENSE.txt</A>,
      or at <A HREF="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">
      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0</A>.
    </P> <P>
      The Bibop theme is copyrighted under the supplied GPL 2 license.
    </P>
  </SECTION>

  <SECTION name="Contributed Documentation" id="doc_contrib">
    <P>
      <EM>Contributed Documentation</EM> is documentation that has been provided by people that are not
      core JWebMail developers but have managed to run JWebMail on different platforms/systems and taken the
      effort to provide you with some sort of extra documentation (thanks a lot, BTW). I (Sebastian
      Schaffert) have not tested what you will find here.
    </P>
  </SECTION>

  <SECTION name="Credits" id="credits">
    <P>
      Appreciation to all who reported bugs and made suggestions to
      improve JWebMail.
    </P>
    <P>
      Some, however, I want to mention explicitly:
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>Sebastian Schaffert, schaffer@informatik.uni-muenchen.de,
        who was the project lead before me.</ITEM>
        <ITEM>Devin Kowatch, devink@webengruven.org, for contributing challenge/response authentication</ITEM>
        <ITEM>Homero Borgo, homero@apoyo.uson.mx, for testing JWebMail under rough conditions
          and helping much to find bugs in the product.</ITEM>
        <ITEM>Sebastian's girlfriend for her patience and the cool icons for JWebMail 0.5 and 0.6</ITEM>
        <ITEM>The people at Bibop in Italy, especially Gianugo Rabellino and Ricardo Rocha for
          doing the Bibop Theme and lots of inspirations</ITEM>
        <ITEM>Sacha Berger, bergers@informatik.uni-muenchen.de, for some very interesting
        discussions about how to do things right.:-)</ITEM>
      </LIST>
    </P>
    <P>
      <STRONG>Blaine Simpson, blaine.simpson@admc.com</STRONG>
    </P>
  </SECTION>
</GUIDE>
